Finding Aid for the Amiri Baraka Papers LSC.0491
UCLA Library Special Collections
Amiri Baraka papers
1952-1966
UCLA Library Special Collections
Baraka, Amiri
LSC.0491
1.6 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
Amiri Baraka (1934-2014) was the founder and editor of the literary journals Yugen and Kulchur. An outspoken public intellectual, he was the author of poetry, plays, novels, and essays. The collection consists of poetry manuscripts and correspondence submitted to Baraka while editor of Yugen. Some material relates to Kulchur.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 994622893606533
Biography
Amiri Baraka was born Everett LeRoi Jones on October 7, 1934 in Newark, New Jersey. He attended Rutgers University and graduated from Howard University. After some graduate study in New York City, he joined the U.S. Air Force. Upon his discharge he returned to New York and took up writing poetry in earnest. To distribute the work of other poets as well, he and his wife, Hettie Cohen, founded Totem Press and the literary journal Yugen. With the poet Diana di Prima, he also founded the journal Kulchur. Always politically active, throughout the 1960s, he became more radical and embraced Black nationalism. Later, he distanced himself from Black nationalism to adopt a more globalistic Communism. For the rest of his life, he would be known as much for his controversial political views as for his poetry. Baraka died on January 9, 2014 in the city of his birth.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of correspondence as well as poetry manuscripts submitted to Amiri Baraka (LeRoi Jones), editor of Yugen. Some material relates to Kulchur. Correspondents include Jonas Mekas, John Rechy, Diane Wakoski, and Philip Whalen.
Organization and Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by correspondent and manuscript author.
Beat generation -- Poetry.; Manuscripts for publication; Periodical editors -- United States -- Archives.; African American poets -- Archives.; African American dramatists -- Archives.; African American authors -- Archives.; Baraka, Amiri, 1934-2014--Archives.
- Correspondence and Manuscripts
  - A, 1959 (Box 1)
    Scope and Content
    Includes letter and poem by Alan Ansen.
  - Abrams, Sam, 1960-1966 (Box 1)
    Six poems; one letter; annotated typescript draft and published copy of Barbara (Ferry Press, 1966).
  - Allen, Donald, 1960-1964 (Box 1)
    Eight letters, review of The Dharma Bums by James Schuyler.
  - B, 1959-1966 (Box 1)
  - Bergé, Carol, 1962-1966 (Box 1)
    Two letters; eighteen poems.
  - Berrigan, Ted, undated (Box 1)
    One letter enclosing poems by Larry Swingle.
  - Blackburn, Paul, 1959 (Box 1)
    Chain letter.
  - Blaser, Robin, undated (Box 1)
    Two poems.
  - Booth, Luella, undated (Box 1)
    Fourteen poems; one-act play; Love Is Bright Round My Shoulder (Toronto: J.H. Bell & Son).
  - Bremser, Ray, 1958-1965 (Box 1)
    Eight letters; approximately 115 poems.
  - Briggs, Harold, undated (Box 1)
    Three poems.
  - Brodey, Jim, 1963-1966 (Box 1)
    Eleven poems; record review; two letters.
  - C, 1960-1964 (Box 1)
    Includes post card from Kirby Congdon.
  - Caplan, Ron, undated (Box 1)
  - Carroll, Paul, 1959 (Box 1)
    Two letters.
  - Creeley, Robert, undated (Box 1)
    One letter.
  - Crews, Judson C, undated (Box 1)
  - D, circa 1963 (Box 1)
  - Dawson, Fielding, 1958-1962 (Box 1)
    Nine drawings; three letters; typed manuscripts.
  - Di Prima, Diane, 1959-1966 (Box 1)
    Four letters; thirteen poems.
  - Dorn, Edward, 1960-1964 (Box 1)
    Approximately sixty letters; four poems; annotated manuscript for The Newly Fallen.
  - Edson, Russell, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Eigner, Larry, 1960-1965 (Box 2)
    Ten letters; nine poems.
  - F, 1960-1964 (Box 2)
    Includes "Poetry and Politics" by Larry Fagin; letter and poem from Vincent Ferrini.
  - Fallon, Tom, 1964 (Box 2)
    Letter; prose manuscripts.
  - Finstein Max, 1960-1964 (Box 2)
    Three letters; statement about LeRoi Jones' 1961 arrest on obscenity charges.
  - Fles, John, 1959-1960 (Box 2)
    Five letters; eight poems; manuscripts; book review.
  - G, 1958-1966 (Box 2)
    Includes post card from E.V. Griffith.
  - Gallatin, David, 1963 (Box 2)
    Two poems; one letter.
  - Gallup, Dick, 1962-1963 (Box 2)
    Nine poems.
  - Guillén, Nicolás, undated (Box 2)
    Includes poem by Guillen; two poems by Silvano Lora; flyers.
  - H, circa 1961 (Box 2)
    Includes essay by Bobb Hamilton.
  - Hollo, Anselm, 1960-1963 (Box 2)
    Nine poems; two letters.
  - Irby, Kenneth, 1962-1966 (Box 2)
    Three letters; six poems.
  - J, circa 1957 (Box 2)
    Includes collage material from Ray Johnson.
  - Jonas, Stephen, 1953-1963 (Box 2)
    Approximately six letters and eighty-five poems.
  - K, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Kaplan, Allan, undated (Box 2)
    Fifteen poems.
  - Katzman, Allen, 1966 (Box 2)
    One letter; eight poems.
  - Kelly, Robert, 1966 (Box 2)
    Post card; seven poems.
  - Kgositsile, K. William, undated (Box 2)
    Seven poems.
  - L, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
  - Loewinsohn, Ron, 1957-1963 (Box 3)
    Uncut galley proofs; twenty-nine letters; approximately twenty-five poems.
  - M, 1959-1964 (Box 3)
    Includes two poems by Christopher Maclaine; one poem by Clarence Major.
  - Malanga, Gerard, 1966 (Box 3)
    One letter; six poems.
  - Marshall, Edward, 1957-1961 (Box 3)
    Two letters; seventeen poems.
  - Mekas, Jonas, undated (Box 3)
    One letter; two poems; clippings.
  - Meltzer, David, 1959-1964 (Box 3)
    Six letters; post card; four poems.
  - Metcalf, Paul C, 1962-1964 (Box 3)
    Three letters; two poems.
  - Moraff, Barbara, 1958-1962 (Box 3)
    Approximately eight letters and fifty-six poems.
  - Olson, Charles, 1965 (Box 3)
    One letter; assorted writings.
  - Oppenheimer, Joel, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Owens, Rochelle, 1960 (Box 3)
    Two letters; nineteen poems.
  - Padgett, Ron, 1964 (Box 4)
    Twenty-one poems; four letters.
  - Perrault, John, 1964 (Box 4)
    Five poems; one letter.
  - Planz, Allen, undated (Box 4)
    Ten poems; one letter.
  - Polite, Allen, undated (Box 4)
    One manuscript.
  - R, 1961 (Box 4)
  - Randall, Margaret, 1966 (Box 4)
    One letter and three poems.
  - Rechy, John, 1962 (Box 4)
    Three letters.
  - Rice, William J, undated (Box 4)
    Five copies of printed, unbound manuscript "Poems."
  - Robbins, Tom, undated (Box 4)
  - Rumaker, Michael, 1961-1965 (Box 4)
    Six letters; two poems
  - S, 1960-1963 (Box 4)
    Includes letter from Michael Shayer; letters and poems from George Stanley.
  - Snyder, Gary, 1958-1960 (Box 4)
    Three letters; broadside; four poems, including an annotated manuscript of "The Berry Feast."
  - Sorrentino, Gilbert, 1960-1966 (Box 4)
    Book review; three poems; three letters; short story.
  - Spellman, A.B, 1958 (Box 4)
  - T, circa 1961 (Box 4)
  - Thomas, Lorenzo (aka Lorenzo Toumes?), 1964-1965 (Box 4)
    Two letters; four poems.
  - Towle, Tony, 1966 (Box 4)
    One letter; three poems.
  - Tzara, Tristan, undated (Box 4)
    One poem [in French].
  - V, 1961-1963 (Box 4)
  - W, 1959-1963 (Box 4)
    Includes letters from Douglas Woolf.
  - Wakoski, Diane, 1962 (Box 4)
    Three letters; nineteen poems.
  - Whalen, Philip, 1952-1964 (Box 4)
    Twenty-two letters; eleven poems; prose manuscript.
  - Wieners, John, 1957-1966 (Box 4)
    Two letters; thirteen poems.
  - Williams, William Carlos, 1958 (Box 4)
  - Yorck, R. L, undated (Box 4)
    One letter; two poems.
  - Unidentified, 1957-1963 (Box 4)